<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Command Line | CEK.io]]></title>
  <link href="http://cek.io/blog/categories/command-line/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cek.io/"/>
  <updated>2019-06-27T15:15:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://cek.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Chris Eaves-Kohlbrenner]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[c.kohlbrenner@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Hammer of JavaScript (and Other Tools for Other Nails)]]></title>
    <link href="http://cek.io/blog/2016/02/08/javascript-hammer/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-08T16:10:04+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://cek.io/blog/2016/02/08/javascript-hammer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The one where I get a harsh reminder to question my instincts from a real-life experience of <a href="https://xkcd.com/1319/">this XKCD comic</a>.</em></p>

<p>As a mental exercise, a friend proposed the following potential interview question: given a directory with 10,000 files of text, how would you extract all the phone numbers from that directory into a single file?</p>

<p>My immediate thought: this would be a basic assessment of someone&rsquo;s knowledge of:</p>

<ol>
<li>regular expressions to match patterns of numbers</li>
<li>how to programmatically read/write files</li>
<li>basic algorithmic complexity for iterating through files quickly.</li>
</ol>


<p>I even knew how I&rsquo;d implement it: use node&rsquo;s filesystem module to read the files, parse them for regex matches, and write all matches to a new file.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/hammer-nail.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>I was intrigued enough that I decided to prove it out. I wrote a basic phone number regex by hand (<code>\d{3}(-|\s|\.)?\d{3}(-|\s|\.)?\d{4}\</code> (for 3 digits, 3 digits, and 4 digits separated by hyphens, periods, spaces, or nothing), and looked into popular phone number regexes. I realized how unfamiliar I am with <a href="https://nodejs.org/api/fs.html">Node&rsquo;s filesystem module</a> (<code>readdir</code> and <code>readFile</code> and <code>writeFile</code>). Then I got curious about <a href="https://docs.npmjs.com/getting-started/publishing-npm-packages">publishing npm packages</a>. Before I knew it, I&rsquo;d spent a couple hours and produced a <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/collect-phone-numbers">somewhat polished npm project</a> for this hypothetical task.</p>

<p>And it was all wrong.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>The thought process I used was logical. My work as a software engineer focuses almost entirely on the web, JavaScript, build tools, UI features, HTTP servers. I&rsquo;m comfortable with databases, front- and back-end code, version control, and countless other things. But that&rsquo;s a small subset of software! Classic hammer/nail.</p>

<p>To Wikipedia:
<blockquote><p>Software: any set of instructions that directs a computer to perform specific tasks or operations.</p><footer><strong>Wikipedia <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software</a> &ldquo;Software&rdquo;</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Software is about problem-solving. But problems can&rsquo;t be solved well without being understood. And they won&rsquo;t be well understood if we assume we should use the same solution every time. There&rsquo;s something to be said for using the tools you know, but software also requires a humility to recognize when a given tool is the wrong one.</p>

<p>In this case, I skipped the step of analyzing the problem. I didn&rsquo;t think about the specifics of the problem, the tradeoffs of time, or the alternative solutions I could choose. This was a one-time, approximate task. It was unlikely to be repeated often enough to make automating worthwhile. And yet I instinctually went with what I knew, implementing a &ldquo;good&rdquo;, &ldquo;complete&rdquo; solution that was really just a picture of overengineering.</p>

<p><img class="left <a" src="href="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/automation.png">https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/automation.png</a>" width="300"></p>

<p>For a problem like this, why use another language or abstraction when it can be done via the command line, the text interface for the computer itself and a much more direct interface with the filesystem? Why use a language like JavaScript that&rsquo;s best suited for the web or pull in Node just for the sake of using a tool I know?</p>

<p>These are questions I won&rsquo;t soon forget to ask myself when I take on a new problem. Hopefully that&rsquo;ll prevent me from falling into traps that webcomics are made of. I know for sure that, next time I&rsquo;m presented with a problem of finding text within a filesystem, I&rsquo;ll remember that tools like <code>grep</code> were made for exactly that. A simpler, less time-instensive, and more appropriate solution.</p>

<p><code>egrep "\b[[:digit:]]{3}(-|\s|.)?[[:digit:]]{3}(-|\s|.)?[[:digit:]]{4}\b" ./* &gt; ./nums.txt</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
